George Safford Torrey Papers 1982.0008
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
George Safford Torrey Papers
undated, 1910-1980
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
1982.0008
7.3 Linear Feet
George Safford Torrey was born 14 March 1891 in Boston, Massachusetts. Torrey was hired in 1915 as an instructor of Botany at the Connecticut Agricultural College and in 1928 received tenure and was appointed Head of the Botany Department. Torrey retired from the University in 1953 and died in 1977.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Acquisition Information
The collection was transferred from the Botany Department.
Arrangement
Series I: Subject Files (1910-1980) is arranged alphabetically and contains Torrey's personal notebooks, correspondence, office memoranda, department records, reports, history, staff information and course descriptions. The series also includes correspondence, promotional literature and research materials concerning the nation-wide Oak Wilt control activities.
Series II: Teaching materials (undated) is arranged by format and includes photographs, stereographs, lantern slides, filmstrips and two stereoscopes. Microfilm copies of articles from the U.S. Department of Agriculture Library have been deaccessioned.
Series III: Botanical Abstracts (undated) is arranged numerically. Abstracts include citations and/or notes from publications or lectures and bibliographical information. A list of missing pages can be found in Box 11, ff #74.
Series IV: American Association of University Professors (AAUP) (1936-1961) contains annual reports and correspondence, arranged chronologically.
Series V: University Senate (1923-1956) includes institutional reports and policies concerning tenure, comprehensive examinations, absence and similar issues. The series is arranged alphabetically.
Series VI: Audiovisual materials (1969).
Biography
George Safford Torrey was born 14 March 1891 in Boston, Massachusetts. He graduated from Harvard College in 1913 with a B.A. degree and continued his study in the Graduate School of Arts and Sciences, Harvard University (1915, M.A. in Botany) and diplome d'Etudes Superieures (Botanique, University of Paris, 1919).
Prior to his employment in Storrs, Torrey had worked at Gray Herbarium (Harvard) and the Department of Agriculture (Newfoundland). Torrey was hired in 1915 as an instructor of Botany at the Connecticut Agricultural College. He received tenure in 1928 and was appointed Head of the Botany Department. Torrey served as the secretary of the Faculty, Registrar and chairman of the Committee on Scholastic Standing, in addition to guest performances on the organ and bassoon at off campus events.
Torrey retired from the University in 1953 but continued to assist in the revision of the Connecticut Catalog of Flowering Plants and Ferns.
G. Safford Torrey died in 1977. Soon after his death, the University of Connecticut named the building housing the Life Sciences departments in his honor.
Scope and Content
The collection contains the personal and professional papers of G. Safford Torrey,> longtime professor of Botany at the University. Materials in the collection include notebooks, correspondence, memoranda, administrative (department) records, reports, photographs, and various types of slides, and filmstrips.
Photocopies; Typescripts; Botany; Universities and colleges; Manuscripts (document genre); Histories; Abstracts (summaries); Examinations; Botanists; Notes; Societies; Monographs; United States (nation); Speeches (documents); Obituaries; Lantern slides; Filmstrips; Connecticut (state); Administrators; Photographs; Administrative records; Financial Records; Minutes (administrative records); School Records; Academic freedom; Oak wilt; Moving images; Correspondence; Comprehensive examinations; Notebooks; Education; Publications (documents); University of Connecticut. University Senate; Connecticut Agricultural College; Connecticut State College. Department of Botany; Connecticut State College. Department of Botany; American Association of University Professors. University of Connecticut Chapter
- Series I: Subject Files, 1910-1980
  - Advancement of Teaching, undated, 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Angiosperms, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Botany Department
    - Awards and Exams, 1931-1944 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Blakeslee, Albert F. [see also "History"], undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence
      - Burt, E. A., 1932-1935 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Torrey, George Safford, 1950-1952 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Instruments and plants, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Laboratory facilities and courses, undated, 1930, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - President's office, 1931-1952 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Course proposals, undated, 1953-1955 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Fernald, Merritt Lyndon [memorial], 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - History, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Intercollegiate bulletins, undated, 1924-1944 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Information on plants, 1933-1954 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Introduction to GST/ GST Department records, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Jansson, K. P., 1941-1952 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - New Quarters, 1929-1951 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Planting list, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Staff and History Records, undated, 1951-1955 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - UConn office correspondence, 1945-1956 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Bryophytas: Working notes, undated, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Cartledge, J. L., undated, 1938-1943 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Catalog of Flora in Connecticut, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Connecticut Agricultural College, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence [Inquiries], undated, 1955, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Culture records, 1910-1956 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Department correspondence, 1915-1916 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Eames, (Dr.) E. H. and early correspondence [see also ff 63], 1940-1948 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Exams and Faculty action, 1933-1936, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - For new release, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Hubbard, Mary, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Instruction for use of Lab Appliances, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Inventories, 1924-1945 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Mimeographed materials—USDA [re: lantern slides], 1925-1932 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Newcomer, Earl H., 1951, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Note Books, 1913-1940 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Notes and Letters, 1915-1949 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Notes for Typing and revisions, 1954-1966 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Oak Wilt, undated, 1950-1953
    - Arkansas, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Cures, 1950-1953 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Fungicide, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - General, 1950-1953 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Illinois, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Indiana, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Iowa, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Maryland, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Michigan, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Minnesota, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Missouri, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - New York, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Ohio, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Organization, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Pathology, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Pennsylvania, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Publicity, 1950-1952 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Research, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Tennessee, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - West Virginia, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Wisconsin, 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Organization: Torrey Botanical Club, undated, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Outline for Students Preparing for Comprehensive Exams, 1933-1934 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Photographs and labels—Display cases, undated (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Photographs—Eames, E. H. [see also ff 28], undated (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Photographs and negatives—Plants, undated, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Quarantine & Inspection Port—New York, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Slips and notes for Connecticut Botany Secretary, undated (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Sphagna, undated (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Teaching outlines, 1937-1962 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Torrey Building, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Waterman Lamp, undated, 1935-1945 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Welsh Bryophytas—Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 71)
- Series II: Teaching materials, undated
  - Stereoscopes, undated; (2 items) (Box 3)
  - Photographs and stereographs, undated (Box 4)
  - Lantern slides, undated (Box 5, Box 6, Box 7, Box 8)
  - Filmstrips and Mimeographed materials, undated (Box 10)
- Series III: Botanical Abstracts, undated
  - Page numbers (Box 11)
    - 1 - 200 (Box 11, Folder 72)
    - 201 - 400 (Box 11, Folder 73)
    - 401 - 600 (Box 11, Folder 74)
    - 601 - 800 (Box 11, Folder 75)
    - 801 - 1000 (Box 11, Folder 76)
    - 1001 - 1200 (Box 12, Folder 77)
    - 1201 - 1400 (Box 12, Folder 78)
    - 1401 - 1600 (Box 12, Folder 79)
    - 1601 - 1800 (Box 12, Folder 80)
    - 1801 - 2014 (Box 12, Folder 81)
- Series IV: American Association of University Professors (AAUP), 1936-1961
  - 1936 (Box 13, Folder 82)
  - 1937 (Box 13, Folder 83)
  - 1938 (Box 13, Folder 84)
  - 1939 (Box 13, Folder 85)
  - 1940 (Box 13, Folder 86)
  - 1941 (Box 13, Folder 87)
  - 1950 (Box 13, Folder 88)
  - 1951 (Box 13, Folder 89)
  - 1952 (Box 13, Folder 90)
  - 1955 (Box 13, Folder 91)
  - 1958 (Box 13, Folder 92)
  - 1961 (Box 13, Folder 93)
- Series V: University Senate, undated, 1923-1956
  - Absence control, 1923 (Box 14, Folder 94)
  - Academic freedom, Tenure and Retirement, 1941-1942 (Box 14, Folder 95)
  - Committee of Comprehensive Exams, 1938-1951 (Box 14, Folder 96)
  - Comprehensive Exam, 1949 (Box 14, Folder 97)
  - Curriculum—Student participation in academics, undated (Box 14, Folder 98)
  - Load committee, 1945-1952 (Box 14, Folder 99)
  - Personnel Advisory committee, 1947 (Box 14, Folder 100)
  - Reports, Faculties and Senates, 1937-1956 (Box 14, Folder 101)
  - Special committee—Functions of the Senate, 1946-1950 (Box 14, Folder 102)
  - Special committee—Salaries and Promotion, 1940-1948 (Box 14, Folder 103)
  - Tenure committee, 1940-1946 (Box 14, Folder 104)
  - Tenure, current, 1947-1948 (Box 14, Folder 105)
- Series VI: Audiovisual materials, 1969
  - Reel to reel tapes
    - 1969 August 7 (Reel 1982-0008.rr1)
    - 1969 August 18 (Reel 1982-0008.rr2)
    - 1969 September 12 (Reel 1982-0008.rr3)
    - 1969 September 23 (Reel 1982-0008.rr4)
    - 1969 October 8 (Reel 1982-0008.rr5)
    - 1969 October 22 (Reel 1982-0008.rr6)